<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>education on Doug Johnson</title>
    <link>/tags/education/</link>
    <description>Recent content in education on Doug Johnson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/education/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the Impact of State Education Policies in India Using ASER and Synthetic Controls</title>
      <link>/post/2021-08-23-estimating-the-impact-of-state-education-policies-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021-08-23-estimating-the-impact-of-state-education-policies-in-india/</guid>
      <description>In a recent article Andres Parrado and I take a look at the two main sources of learning outcomes data in India – NAS and ASER – and conclude that a) NAS data is (most likely) completely unreliable and b) ASER data, while reliable, is a bit noisy.
The implications for people considering using NAS data are pretty clear – you shouldn’t. For ASER, the implications are a bit murkier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How India Compares to the World on Learning Outcomes</title>
      <link>/post/2021-03-14-how-india-compares-to-the-world-on-education-performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021-03-14-how-india-compares-to-the-world-on-education-performance/</guid>
      <description>Researchers at the World Bank recently released an excellent new dataset on learning outcomes by country.The dataset is here and a journal article describing the dataset is here. This is the first dataset on learning outcomes (rather than educational attainment) which includes most low income countries. (Hanushek and Woesmann created a cross country dataset on learning outcomes some time back but it only included 77 countries.)
How well does India do according to the HLO dataset?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>